Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection:
Calendar of the Manuel E. Gondra Manuscript Collection, The University of Texas Library, prepared by Carlos Eduardo Castañeda, University of Texas, and Jack Autrey Dabbs, AM College of Texas. México: Editorial Jus, 1952.
- Eighteenth Century Documents (1778-1799)
  - 1812 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] 1787 (?). 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 50-51. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546b)
    Needs of presidio at the river ford.
  - 1813 _____. [Carta sin dirección ni lugar.] Paraíso (?). 1787 (?). 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 36v. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ax])
    Advice on construction of a fort.
  - 1814 Alós, Joaquín. De la planta Ibirá y del Cáñamo que de ella se saca llamado comunmente Caraguatá. 1787 (?). Two modern copies, each 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 6-8. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-24-B and AGI 124-4-7, respectively. (Box [MG 1474c])
    Industrial uses of Caraguatá (twine).
  - 1815 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Emboscada, January 1, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 10. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546p])
    Removal of garrison to Villena; disposition of prisoners.
  - 1816 _____. Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, January 5, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 7v-8. Modern copy from Vol. 3420, Archivo Nacional. (Box [MG 546m])
    Theft of 25 horses; suspicions of Machicuis and Lenguas.
  - 1817 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] January 5, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 26v-27. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546aj])
    Indian theft of horses, conversion of natives.
  - 1818 _____. Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, January 7, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 10v-11. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546q])
    Attempts of prisoners to escape; dissatisfaction of Tobas and Mocovís.
  - 1819 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Emboscada, January 14, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 8v-9. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546n])
    Rumor of Indian attack on Guarepotí; suspicions of Enimagás and Tobas.
  - 1820 Biedma, Francisco de. [Carta a Su Alteza informando detalladamente sobre las reducciones de los Chiriguanos.] Cochabamba, January 15, 1788. 31 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-7-I. (Box [MG 1054])
    Topography of region; ethnological data on Indians, name, location, and relevant data on each reduction; work of Francisco Ramón de Herbozo, Lorenzo Ortiz, Manuel Gil, Vicente Lobo, Lorenzo Raucos, Tomás de Leso, Joaquín Beltrán, Francisco del Pilar, Pedro de Santiago, Gerónimo Bejarano, José de Buceta, García Hurtado de Mendoza; reference and brief descriptions of Tucurú; fort of Saypurú; plantations of Piray, Florida, Cabezas, Abapó, Fort San Carlos; Indians on Río Parapití; Río Grande; San Miguel de los Chiquitos; Laguna; Tobas Indians; Partido de Villa grande; labors of Juan de Torres, S. J.; Río Parabanó; Fray Narciso de Vega Oteo; Pedro de Santiago; Pueblo de Nuestra Señora del Pilar de la Florida; Pueblo y Misión de Nuestra Señora del Carmen de Cabeza; Pueblo y Misión de la Santísima Trinidad de Abapó; Pueblo de San Rafael de Mozavi; Pueblo de Igmirí; Sierra de los campos, (Opabusú); Fray Tomás Nicolás; expedition of Alejandro Salvatierra; frustrated attack of Maruama; Militia Captain Canderugua; hopes for aid from Asunción and Jujuy.
    Printed: MA IV, 648-669, (folios 1-28).
  - 1821 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, January 23, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 9-10. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546o])
    Attack on Guarepotí; failure of spies; trip to Tobatí.
  - 1822 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Peñón, January 23, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 30. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ao])
    Mission of Talavera; use of an old Machicui woman as messenger.
  - 1823 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Emboscada, February 6, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 28v-29. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546am])
    Obedience to real cédulas and revision of accounts.
  - 1824 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Emboscada, February 6, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 27. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ak])
    Failure to contact Machicuis; their fear of Tobas and Lenguas.
  - 1825 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] February 18, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 29-30. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420 (Box [MG 546an])
    War between Tobas and Lenguas; end of smallpox epidemic; war between Enimagás and Pitilagas; attacks on Spanish at Guarepotí.
  - 1826 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a Antonio Porlier comunicando haber dado cuenta a Antonio Valdés de los diferentes productos del Paraguay.] Asunción, April 13, 1788. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-24-B. (Box [MG 1474a])
    Discussion of caraguatá.
  - 1827 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melodia, April 19, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 32v-33. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ar])
    Reception of delegation from the Machicuis and Lenguas.
  - 1828 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Paraíso de Melodia, April 21, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 27v-28. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546a)
    Treatment of Lenguas and Enimagás for peace; return of stolen animals.
  - 1829 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melodia, April 25, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 25-26. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ai])
    Indian peace proposal; horse theft; conversion of the Indians.
  - 1830 Carlos IV. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós aprobando sus esfuerzos relativos a la historia natural.] Aranjuez, June, 1788. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 6-7. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-24-A. (Box [MG 1470b])
    Concerning Félix de Azara.
  - 1831 Alós, Joaquín. [Mandamiento a Francisco Cabañas que informa del estado de la reducción de San Francisco de Paula de indios guayanás a distancia de doce leguas de este pueblo.] Pueblo del Corpus, July 4, 1788. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-15. (Box [MG 546a])
  - 1832 Cabañas y Ampuero, Francisco. [Informe descriptivo sobre la población San Francisco de Paula de indios guayanás.] San Francisco de Paula? July 5, 1788. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 2-6. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-5. (Box [MG 564b])
  - 1833 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Lorenzo Gaona.] August 19, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 6. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546i])
    Loss of cattle by the garrison at Villena; surrender of the Enimagás.
  - 1834 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, August 27, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 33. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546as])
    Removal of troops from Melódia, leaving the arms.
  - 1835 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Emboscada, September 1, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 23-24. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ae])
    Reduction of Remolinos; disappearance of smallpox; new road found to Río Pilcomayo.
  - 1836 Porlier, Antonio. [Carta al gobernador intendente de Cochabamba transmitiendo los deseos de S. M. acerca de poner en ejecución el plan de gobierno propuesto por el destinatario.] San Ildefonso, September 10, 1788. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 618a])
    Missions of Chiriguanos and other Indians.
  - 1837 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, September 15, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 24. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546af])
    Retreat of Machicuis for fear of smallpox; nearness of the Enimagás and Lenguas.
  - 1838 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Paraíso de Melódia, September 21, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 24v-25. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ah])
    Raid of Enimagás; dependence of Machicuis; need for another fort.
  - 1839 Loreto, Marqués de. [Pasaporte concedido al presbítero Francisco Ancheta para hacer un viaje a Asunción.] Buenos Aires, September 28, 1788. 1 l. 21 × 30 cm. Original MS. (Box [MG 2038])
  - 1840 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, October 24, 1788. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 24. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ag])
    Provisions furnished refugees from the smallpox plague.
  - 1841 Velasco, Luis. [Carta a Antonio Porlier sobre los eclesiásticos beneméritos en esta diócesis.] Asunción, November 13, 1788. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 125-7-2. (Box [MG 1653])
    Pedro Zamudio, Juan Bernardo, Martín de Sotomayor, Bartolomé Amarilla, Miguel Pérez Bustillo, Pedro Regalado, Miguel Antonio Antúnez, Miguel Montiel, and Agustín Curtido.
  - 1842 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Emboscada, December 18, 1788. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 22v-23. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546ad])
    Narrow escape of the theif Rodríguez; return of a stolen horse.
  - 1843 Colegio de San Carlos, Gobernador de los Estudios del. [Petición al gobernador de la provincia sobre el sueldo del catedrático Juan Antonio de Zavala del Colegio de San Carlos.] Asunción, December 12, 1788? 2 l. 21 × 30 cm. f. 3-4. Original. (Box [MG 1973b])
    Salary promised to him by Pedro Melo de Portugal. Includes certificate of Joaquín Alós, Asunción, December 12, 1788.
  - 1844 Zavala, Juan Antonio de? [Carta a Martínez pidiendo el valor de 1500 arrobas de yerba y su respuesta.] 1788? 1 l. 15 × 21 cm. f. 5. Original. (Box [MG 1973c])
  - 1845 Haenke, Tadeo. Noticias sobre los Pueblos interiores incognitos de la Cordillera de Yndios Chiriguanaes y Chaneces, comunicadas al Señor Dn. Franco de Viedma. 1788? 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 120-4-22-A. (Box [MG 1462])
    Topography of area involved; course of Parapití River and mountains between it and Río Pilcomayo.
  - 1846 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Emboscada, January 2, 1789. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 2. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546c])
    Robbery of Alejo Acosta's pretal.
  - 1847 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Emboscada, January 2, 1789. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 7v. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 5461])
    Indian peace proposals.
  - 1848 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a Antonio Valdés sobre los despachos expedidos a favor de José Antonio Yegros y José de Espínola y sobre reducciones del Gran Chaco por el presbítero Francisco Amansio González.] Asunción, January 13, 1789. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 124-4-7. (Box [MG 1113])
  - 1849 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melódia, January 18, 1789. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 7. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546k])
    Recovery of Machicuis; peace with the Lenguas.
  - 1850 _____. [Carta al secretario Lorenzo Gaona.] Melódia, February 16, 1789. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 6-7. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546j])
    Stolen pretal of Alejo Acosta; efforts to make peace with Lenguas and Enimagás.
  - 1851 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Melódia, March 7, 1789. 3 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 41v-43. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546bh])
    Continued thefts and insults by Indians.
  - 1852 Bogarín, Antonio. [Carta al gobernador del Paraguay suplicando se le contribuya por razón de sínodo.] Reducción de San Antonio, March 28, 1789. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 8v-9. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-B, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 334e])
    Statement of services among Toba Indians.
  - 1853 Presilla, Juan José de la. [Carta a S. M. en que suplica se confiera a Pedro Vicente Cañete y Domínguez la plaza de fiscal en la Real Audiencia de Charcas.] Madrid, April 1789. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-3. Modern copy from Est. Aud. Charcas, Leg. 1, No. 6. (Box [MG 1402a])
  - 1854 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós y Brú.] Asunción, May 6, 1789. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 65v-66. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bt])
    Request for reimbursement of expenses during three years in the Chaco.
  - 1855 [Croix, Caballero de] Virrey del Perú. [Inconvenientes comerciales y políticos que resultan de la distribución de las provincias del Alto Perú entre los Virreynatos de Buenos Aires y Perú.] Lima, May 16, 1789. 39 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 110-1-16. No. 1, with two typewritten copies, each 17 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 94])
    Intercolonial trade; value of mines of Upper Peru; cost of royal armada; poor communication between colonies; uselessness of intendancies; administration of customs and royal treasury; need for rectification of boundaries of Lima and Jujuy; jurisdiction of the Audiencia of los Charcas; Provinces of Paraguay, Tucumán, Salta, Cuyo, La Paz, Chucuita, Puno, Carabaya, Azangaro, Lampa; Bishop of Cuzco; governmental agencies: Junta Superior de Buenos Aires, Real Audiencia del Cuzco, and Tribunal de Cuentas; revolt of Caciques Tinta and Chayanta; charges made in provinces of Zicacica (Sicasica), Larecaxas, Pacaxes, Carangas, Callao; civil disturbance in mines of Lica Cota (Puna Province) in 1601-7; difficulty in defense of coast caused by separation of viceroyalty; relations with Panamá, Chiloé, Valdivia, Isla de Juan Fernández; interception of commerce by corsairs; Tacna, Tarapacá; Arica; Iquique; defenselessness of Atacama from Buenos Aires; Cobija, Lima, Arequipa; English contraband trade; danger to Guayaquil, Realezo, Sonsonate, and Acapulco from pirates; problem of mines of Potosí; depopulation of Huancavelica; mines in Guarochiri; problem of Portuguese threats and contraband trade; loss of Sacramento; defenselessness of Río Grande, Río de la Plata, Río Paraná, Río Ithenés, Mamoré, Lagunaminí; cold reception of plan of Joaquín de Espinosa for road from Paraguay to Salta and Jujuy; ease of advance along the Río Beni and Marmoré to Apolobamba and Carabaya; boundaries on the Amazon; trade in Hierba Maté; dried meat; sale of meat to foreigners; trade in skins; whale hunting; foreign ships on the Patagonia coast; ports of Aranta and Ilo.
    Printed: ABJ II, Anexo 83, 181-196.
  - 1856 _____. El virrey del Perú, Caballero de Croix, representa á S. M. los graves inconvenientes que a producido el establecimiento de Intendencias en aquel territorio, y la urgente necesidad de su extincion y de que se repongan los Correjimientos. May 16, 1789. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 112-7-16. (Box [MG 1231])
    Effect of intendancy system on Panamá, Valdivia, Chile, Juan Fernández, and La Plata.
  - 1857 Alós, Joaquín. Relacion del tiempo esperimentado en los seis primeros meses de este año, y demas particularidades.... Asunción, June 30, 1789. 5 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-12-B. (Box [MG 1837])
    Climate, epidemics, and agriculture in the province.
  - 1858 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, July 1, 1789. 4 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 60v-63. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bq])
    Need for reinforcements; efforts to pacify the Tobas and Lenguas.
  - 1859 _____. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, July 5, 1789. 1 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 63. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546br])
    Ruses of Indians to steal horses and cows.
  - 1860 CONSEJO DE INDIAS. [Dictamen fiscal sobre el recurso que dirigieron a S. M. los curas de la catedral y parroquias de la Encarnación del Paraguay y auto en que aconseja que se remitan al obispo una copia del recurso.] Madrid, July 28-August 7, 1789. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-21-B, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 1914])
  - 1861 Machado, Francisco. Por parte de Dn. Pedro Vicente Cañete Teniente Asesor de la Intendencia... se... solicita exercer las mismas facultades que el Intendte en sus ausencias.... Madrid, July 28, 1789. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-3-21-G. (Box [MG 1842.])
    Opinion on petition written for the Contaduría General.
  - 1862 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a S. M. sobre el establecimiento de cementerios fuera de poblados; datos estadísticos del Paraguay y ciudad de Asunción.] Asunción, November 13, 1789. 6 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-18, with two typewritten copies, each 3 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 316])
  - 1863 Velasco, Luis de. [Memorial a su Majestad referente a cementerios fuera de las iglesias.] Asunción, November 13, 1789. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-18, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 159])
  - 1864 Loreto, Marqués de. [Carta a Antonio Porlier sobre las facilidades que han de darse al Dean de la Iglesia Catedral de Asunción.] Buenos Aires, November 25, 1789. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-6-6-B. (Box [MG 1572])
    Antonio Sánchez; income from tobacco.
  - 1865 _____. [Carta a Fray Antonio Valdez sobre el consumo de tabacco negro del Paraguay.] Buenos Aires, November 25, 1789. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-7-A. (Box [MG 859])
  - 1866 Carlos IV. [Cédula real al obispo del Paraguay concediéndole permiso para tomar las medidas convenientes en lo del reclamo de los curas contra aquél.] Madrid, November 27, 1789. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-6-21-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 162])
  - 1867 CHARCAS, AUDIENCIA DE. [Dictamen del fiscal Villa Urrutia sobre los méritos del plan presentado por el gobernador intendente de Cochabamba sobre el aumento de misiones de Chiriguanos.] La Plata, December 23, 1789. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3-10. Modern copy from AGI 123-1-13. (Box [MG 618b])
    José Buceta, and Fray Manuel Gil.
  - 1868 Alós, Joaquín. Relacion del tiempo experimentado en los seis ultimos meses del año proximo pasado y demas particularidades. Asunción, December 31, 1789. 7 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-12-C. (Box [MG 853])
    Cultivation of tobacco, cotton, tea, corn, manioc, and sugar cane in jurisdictions of Asunción, Villa de Curuguatí, Villa del Espíritu Santo, Población de Concepción, Ñembucú, Remolinos, and Misiones.
  - 1869 Cañete y Domínguez, Vicente. Descripcion Geografica/ Historica, Fisica, y Politica de la Villa Imperial y Cer/ro Rico de Potosí, y/ de los Partidos de Porco, Chayanta/ Chiches ó Tarija, Lipez, y Atacama/ con/ un discurso preliminar, donde se/ manifiesta el Estado politico de esta Villa, des/ de su fundacion, hasta el presente con las Providencias dic/ tadas para su bien regimen, y novedades execu / tadas en su Govierno/ Se trata/ De los minerales y de unas producciones de esta Prova/ explicando el origen, jurisdiccion, y Economía de la/ Super- Intendencia de la Real Mita, casa de/ Moneda, Minas y Banco de Rescates/ que se hallan unidos al/ Gobierno/ con varios dis/cursos y reflecciones sobre/ su atrazo, y medios mas conve/nientes para la mejora de estos quatro bancos/ Dedicado al Exmo. Señor Don Antonio Porlier del Con/sejo de Estado, y Secretario de Gracia y Jus. a del Depo. de Inds./ Por/ el Dr. Dn Pedro Vicente Cañete y Dominguez, Auditor de Guerra/ y Asesor gral. que fué del primer Virrey de Buenos Aires despues de la Capitania general del Paraguay, y Te/niente Letrado actual de esta Prova de Potosí/ Año De 1789/ 31 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from “Biblioteca.” (Box [MG 971])
  - 1870 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a S. M. sobre el fallecimiento del obispo Fray Luis de Velasco, inventario de sus bienes, y la necesidad de proveer su vacancia.] [1789?] 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-17-A, with two typewritten copies, each 2 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 320])
    Data on ecclesiastical government.
  - 1871 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. Carta al gobernador Intendente. (Alós?) 1789? 3 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 66v-68. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3421. (Box [MG 546bu])
    Account of expenses in the Chaco and need for payment.
  - 1872 Scoane, Antonio. [Carta del Gobernador de Santa Cruz a Antonio Porlier, Ministro del Despacho de Indias, en que comunica la celebración de la jura de Carlos IV y homenaje rendido.] Santa Cruz de la Sierra, January 4, 1790. 4 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-25-B. (Box [MG 1472])
  - 1873 Arredondo, Nicolás de. [Carta al gobernador intendente del Paraguay en que comunica notas relativas a depredaciones hechas en Guarepotí e Iguamandiyú por los Payaguás, Sariguás y Mbayás guazús.] Buenos Aires, January 13, 1790. 16 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-12-A. (Box [MG 1831])
    Encroachments of Portuguese and Indians.
  - 1874 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta a S. M. sobre el caracter inquieto y sedicioso del Dr. Juan Bernardo Arroquia, vicario general de este obispado.] Asunción, January 18, 1790. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-1-B, with two typewritten copies, each 5 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 174])
    Impressions of Luis de Velasco, Antonio Sánchez, and Gavino Echevarría; subversive activities.
  - 1875 Arredondo, Nicolás de. [Carta al gobernador intendente en que pide se le mande un informe sobre fuertes necesarios para facilitar la navegación del Río Bermejo.] Buenos Aires, February 13, 1790. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-3. (Box [MG 1130a])
  - 1876 Alós, Joaquín. [Carta al Virrey Nicolás de Arredondo sobre el temor de atropellos de Mbayás a la población de Iguamandiyú.] Asunción, February 13, 1790. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-12-F. (Box [MG 855])
  - 1877 _____. [Carta a Nicolás de Arredondo dando cuenta de haber remitido muestras de las maderas del Paraguay junto con una relación descriptiva.] Asunción, February 20, 1790. 3 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 13-15. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-25-A. (Box [MG 1476c])
  - 1878 _____. Relacion que manifiesta el nombre de las Maderas, sus qualidades, y virtudes de las que se incluyen muestras en un cajon que remite de orden de S. M. Asunción, February 20, 1790. 9 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 4-12. Modern copy from AGI 145-7-25-A. (Box [MG 1476b])
  - 1879 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta al Gobernador Alós.] February 21, 1790. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 73-74. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3425. (Box [MG 546bz])
    Contemplated removal of Tobas to the Reducción de San Antonio.
  - 1880 Alós, Joaquín. Carta [a Fray Antonio Bogarín mandando su retiro de la reducción de San Antonio, con todas los soldados, demás personas y efectos.] Asunción, March 1, 1790. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 10. Modern copy from AGI 123-7-25-B, with two typewritten copies, each 1 p. 21.5 × 32 cm. (Box [MG 334f])
  - 1881 González y Escobar, Juan Francisco Amansio. [Carta a Joaquín de Alós.] Melódia, March 3, 1790. 2 l. 22 × 32 cm. f. 39v-40. Modern copy from Archivo Nacional, Vol. 3420. (Box [MG 546bc])
    Fleeing Enimagás; request for 6 soldiers from José Casal.
  - 1882 Tullo, Rafael. [Carta a Antonio Porlier sobre que conceda a esta Ciudad la facultad de elegir ambos alcaldes añales.] Asunción, March 13, 1790. 1 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 3. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-20-C. (Box [MG 1096b])
  - 1883 ASUNCIÓN, CABILDO DE. [Carta a S. M. pidiendo que la elección de alcalde sea anual y no bienal.] March 13, 1790. 2 l. 17 × 23 cm. f. 1-2. Modern copy from AGI 124-1-20-C. (Box [MG 1096a])
    Signed: Miguel López Zarco, Rafael Tullo, José Joaquín Baldovinos, Francisco Olegario de la Mora, Juan Tomás de Yegros, Juan Antonio Caballero, and Antonio Vigil.
  - 1884 Sá y Faria, José. [Informe a Nicolás de Arredondo sobre las fortalezas establecidas por los portugueses en las tierras españolas.] Buenos Aires, March 24, 1790. 8 l. 17 × 23 cm. Modern copy from AGI 122-7-12-E. (Box [MG 852])